This episode of Real Engineering is brought to you by Brilliant,
a problem solving website that teaches you to think like an engineer.
2019年5月24日 太空叉的猎鹰九号火箭一次发射了60颗卫星
On the 24th of May, SpaceX launched a Falcon 9 rocket filled with 60 satellites into space.
迈出了他们宏伟的Starlink计划的第一步
This marked the beginning of their ambitious new project called “Starlink”
该计划致力于为全球偏远地区提供高通量的互联网服务
which aims to provide high quality broadband internet to the most isolated parts of the planet,
以及为已有覆盖地区提供更低延迟的通信服务
while also providing low latency connectivity to already well connected cities.
太空叉的目标是让大家都能用上
SpaceX aim to make their broadband as accessible as possible,
他们说只要买了其自主研发的披萨盒大小的天线 任何人就都能上网
claiming that anyone will be able to connect to their network if they buy the pizza box-sized antenna
which SpaceX is developing themselves.
而这次发射的60颗卫星 只是其中第一批
This launch of 60 satellites, was just the first of many.
太空叉在未来十年计划发射12000颗卫星
Spacex has 12,000 satellites planned for launch over the next decade,
这会极大增加地球在轨卫星的总数量
dramatically increasing the total amount of spacecraft around Earth's orbit.
这一举动会花掉太空叉数十亿美元 所以希望他们能回本
This will cost SpaceX billions of dollars, so they must have a good reason for doing so.
我们今天来了解一下这个网络是如何工作的 以及它将如何击败现有网络服务商
Let's see how this network will work, and how it will compete with existing internet providers.
回到2015年 马一龙宣布太空叉开始研发一款卫星通信网络
Back in 2015, Elon announced that SpaceX had began working on a communication satellite network,
他说目前全球范围的廉价宽频带卫星间通信有很大的市场需求
stating that there is a significant unmet demand for low-cost global broadband capabilities.
大约在那阵 太空叉在华盛顿州雷德蒙开了新工厂
Around that time, SpaceX opened a new facility in Redmond, Washington
专门研发制造这些新的通信卫星
to develop and manufacture these new communication satellites.
原本计划是在2016年发射两颗原型卫星
The initial plan was to launch two prototype satellites into orbit by 2016
然后让初始的卫星星座在2020年开始运营
and have the initial satellite constellation up and running by 2020.
但太空叉在研发老百姓都会装的廉价接收机上遇到了小麻烦
But the company struggled to develop a receiver that could be easily installed by the user for a low cost,
导致计划有所推迟 直到2018年 两颗原型卫星才发射
this delayed the program and the initial prototype satellites weren't launched until 2018.
在两颗原型卫星——丁丁A和丁丁B发射后
After a successful launch of the two prototypes, Tintin-A and B,
太空叉可以开始测试并修改他们的卫星设计
which allowed SpaceX to test and refine their satellite design,
之后太空叉对Starlink计划公布的内容开始变少
SpaceX kept pretty quiet about what was next for the Starlink project,
直到2018年11月 太空叉拿到了FCC颁发的 发射7500颗卫星入轨的许可
until November 2018 when SpaceX received the approval from the FCC to deploy 7,500 satellites into orbit,
外加之前已经通过审批的4400颗卫星
on top of the 4,400 that were already approved.
在2019年5月24日 首批卫星发射入轨
On May 24th, the first batch of production satellites were launched into orbit
全世界的人们很快发现了划过夜空的这一串卫星
and people around the world quickly started to spot the train of satellites moving across the night sky.
这次发射预示着一个新的潮流要来了
This launch is a sign of things to come,
虽然第一批卫星的功能并不完备
while this initial group of satellites are not fully functional,
它们主要用于测试地球通信系统
they will be used to test things like the earth communications systems
与用于躲避太空垃圾和在寿终正寝时用于离轨的氪推进器
and the krypton thrusters which will be used to autonomously avoid debris and de-orbit the spacecraft
once it has reached the end of its lifecycle.
我们先来看看这些功能
Let's look at these functionalities first.
我们以前已经了解过离子推进器的工作原理 大家可以前去观看以了解更多细节
We have explored how ion thrusters work in the past, which you can watch for more detail,
简言之就是利用电势能将带电粒子发射出去 从而提供推力
but essentially they use electric potential to fire ions out of the spacecraft to provide propulsion.
氙是比较理想的选择 因为它原子量够高 每个原子可以提供更多的动能
Xenon is ideally used, because it has a high atomic mass allowing it to provide more kick per atom,
其自身是惰性气体 存储密度高 可以在航天器上储存很久
while being inert and having a high storage density lending itself to long term storage on a spacecraft.
但太空叉选择了氪 因为氙作为燃料太贵了
However SpaceX opted for krypton, as xenon's rarity makes it a far more expensive propellant.
卫星的离子推进器会首先用于给Starlink卫星升轨
This ion thruster will initially be used to raise the starlink satellites
从星箭分离的440公里提高到最终运行的550公里
from their release orbits at 440 km to their final orbital height of 550 km.
它们还将和卫星上装有的陀螺仪配合
They will also be used in conjunction with on board control momentum gyroscopes located here,
并结合美国政府太空垃圾相撞预警系统
and the US Governments' space debris collision prediction system
让卫星能够自行调整轨道避开太空垃圾
to allow the satellites to adjust their orbits to dodge collisions,
这在之前视频也有提到
which we have also spoken about in more detail in a previous video.
当卫星达到了寿命期限
When the satellites have reached the end of their service life
它们还能用同样的姿态控制器和推进器进行离轨
they can then use the same attitude controls and thrusters to de-orbit the satellite.
太空叉为了防止卫星成为太空垃圾 使用了所有必要的设备
SpaceX have included all the necessary hardware to minimize space debris risk.
在他们的FCC审批申请表中
In their Federal Communications Commission approval application,
他们声称卫星95%的部分会在再入大气时烧毁
they claim that 95% of the satellite will burn up on re-entry.
只有离子推进器的内部结构和碳化硅组件能挺过再入的高温
With only the ion thruster internal structure and silicon carbide components, standing a chance of survival.
只剩碳化硅零件的原因 一方面它是必需零件 一方面是它本身熔点高达2750°C
Those silicon carbide components are likely to survive,
as they are essential materials and thus have an extremely high melting point of 2,750°C.
那么话题就到了卫星的主要功能——通信了
Which brings us to our communications abilities, the primary function of the satellite.
太空叉对卫星的很多细节都讳莫如深
SpaceX have been tight lipped on many of the details of the satellite,
但多亏了FCC的文件 我们了解到卫星有五块1.5千克的碳化硅组件
but thanks to that FCC filing we know that the satellites will contain 5 1.5 kilogram silicon carbide components,
这可能表示每颗卫星会有五个独立的激光发射器
which indicates that each satellite will contain 5 individual lasers.
这些激光 就像我们在地球上用的光纤一样
These lasers, like our fibre optic cables here on earth,
使用光脉冲在卫星之间传递信息
will use light pulses to transmit information between satellites.
相比于在地球 太空中的激光传输有很多优势
Transmitting with light in space offers one massive advantage
over transmitting with light here on earth however.
事实上 光速在不同介质中速度是不同的
The speed of light is not constant in every material, in fact,
光在玻璃中的速度比在真空中慢47%
light travels 47% slower in glass than in a vacuum.
这给Starlink一个极大的优势 很可能成为其首要卖点
This offers Starlink one huge advantage that will likely be it's primary money maker.
它可以提供长距离下的低时延通信
It provides the potential of lower latency information over long distance,
作为简化 我们想象以下数据传输的例子
in simpler terms let's imagine this as a race between data packets.
一名伦敦的用户想要了解纽交所纳斯达克某股票的最新价格
A user in London wants the new adjusted price of a stock on the NASDAQ from the New York stock exchange.
如果该信息使用传统路线 比如AC-2光缆
If this information were to use a typical route, let's say through the AC-2 cable,
往返路程12800公里 介质是光导纤维
which has a return journey of about 12,800 kilometres to make through our glass fibre optic cable.
真空中的光速是299792458米每秒
In a vacuum light travels at a speed of 299,792,458 meters per second.
光纤中的光速取决于折射率 而折射率取决于波长
The speed of travel in glass depends on the refractive index and the refractive index depends on wavelength,
我们取真空中的光速比光纤中快1.47倍
but we will take the reduction as 1.47 times slower than the speed of light in a vacuum.
算下来 数据包来回要走0.063秒
This means the data packet will take roughly 0.063 seconds to make the round trip,
也就是有0.063秒的延迟 或62.7毫秒
and thus has a latency of 0.063 seconds, or 62.7 milliseconds.
外加一些额外的延迟
With the additional steps that add to this latency
比如光缆两端的光电转换
like the conversion of light signals to electrical signals on either end of the optical cable,
数据的队列 以及到终端电脑的时间 最终时延可以达到76毫秒
traffic queues, and the transfer to our final computer terminal, this total time comes out at about 76 ms.
计算出Starlink的延迟要困难得多 因为我们没有现实的例子
Figuring out the latency for Starlink is a lot more difficult, as we have no real world measurements to go by,
但我们可以参考伦敦大学学院通信教授Mark Handley的猜测
but we can make some educated guesses with the help of Mark Handley,
a communications professor in University College London.
第一种延迟产生于上星与下星过程
The first source of latency for Starlink will be during the up and down link process,
我们要让信息从地球上行到卫星 再下行回地球
where we need to transfer our information to and from earth.
这可以通过相控阵列实现
We know this will be done with phase array antenna,
不需要移动天线位置 就能让天线组传输信号
which are radio antenna that can control the direction of their transmission without moving parts,
方法是使用相长干涉和相消干涉控制无线电波束的指向
instead they use destructive and constructive interference to control the direction of the radio wave.
每颗卫星的波束角为81度
Each satellite has a cone beam with a 81 degree range of view.
550公里轨道的卫星可以覆盖宽500公里的地面范围
With an orbit of 550 km each satellite can cover a circular area with a radius of 500 km.
在太空叉原定轨道中 一颗卫星能覆盖1060公里宽
At SpaceX's originally planned orbit this coverage had a radius of 1060 km.
降低卫星轨道高度会减少覆盖范围 但也会减少时延
Lowering the altitude of a satellite decreases the area it can cover,
but also decreases the latency.
这个时延相比于传统的同步轨道通信卫星 降低的效果是非常显著的
This is particularly noticeable for typical communications satellites
operating in geostationary orbit at an altitude of about 36,000 kilometres.
信号以光速往返地面与同步卫星需要240毫秒 是海底光缆的369%
The time it takes data to travel up to the satellite and back down travelling at the speed of light
is around 240 milliseconds 369% slower than our subsea cable.
而Starlink选择了更低的轨道
However, since Starlink is intending to operate at a much lower altitude,
那么上下行的理论时延可以低至3.6毫秒
the up and down link theoretical latency could be as low as 3.6 ms.
因此 太空叉的星座需要的卫星数量相当巨大 才能做到全球覆盖
This is why SpaceX needs so many satellites in their constellation in order to provide worldwide coverage.
每颗Starlink卫星有四个相控阵列天线 位于图中的四个位置
StarlinkEach individual Starlink satellite has four phased array antenna located here, here, here and here.
这些指向性波束就是太空叉向FCC申请的主要内容
This directional beam was an essential part of SpaceX's FCC approval application,
因为上千颗卫星对地胡乱发送无线电波
as thousands of satellites broadcasting undirected radio waves
可能对其他通信方式产生严重干扰
would cause significant amounts of interference with other communication methods.
当一颗Starlink卫星接收到来自地面的数据
Once that data is received by one Starlink satellite,
那么它可以利用激光在卫星之间传输这个数据
it can begin to transmit that information between satellites using lasers.
数据每次在卫星中进行中转
Each time we hop from satellites
都会有一个光电转换的很小的延迟
there will be a small delay as the laser light is converted to an electric signal and back again,
不过延迟很小 可以忽略
but it is too miniscule to consider.
但到了激光这里 事情变得有意思起来了
Things get tricky here with using lasers,
因为我们需要让激光准确发射给相邻的接收卫星
as we need to accurately hit the receiver on neighbouring satellites to transmit that data.
我们先来看一下太空叉提交的星座内容
Let's look at SpaceX's proposed constellation to see how this will work.
太空叉第一阶段的1584颗卫星会占用24个轨道平面
SpaceX's first phase of 1584 satellites will occupy 24 orbital planes,
每个轨道平面倾角53度 有66颗卫星
with 66 satellites in each plane inclined at 53 degrees.
看起来应该是这样
That will look something like this.
在同一轨道面的相邻卫星之间通信相对比较简单
Communication between neighbouring satellites in the same orbital plane is relatively simple,
因为它们的前后相对位置是固定的
as these satellites will remain in relatively stable positions in relation to each other.
这可以提供我们该轨道面下一条线的通信
This gives us a solid line of communication along a single orbital plane,
但在很多情况下 一个轨道面是无法连接两个地点的
but in many cases a single orbital plane will not connect two locations,
所以我们要让不同轨道面的卫星也有通信能力
so we need to be able transfer information between these planes too.
这就需要精准定位 因为不同轨道面的卫星相对速度非常高
This requires precise tracking, as the satellites travelling in neighbouring orbital planes
are travelling incredibly quickly and will come in and out of view.
这就需要Starlink卫星有随时切换到其他卫星的能力
This means the Starlink satellite will need to switch to a new satellite in the network.
而这是需要时间的 最好的例子是1分钟
This can take time, the best figure I could find is about a minute
来自于欧洲航天局数据中继卫星系统
for the European Space Agency's Data Relay Satellite System,
该系统是运营在同步轨道的网络星座
which is a currently operating geostationary internet constellation
设计用于服务欧洲的成像卫星和其他关键用途
designed to serve European imaging satellites, and other time critical applications.
比如偏远地区紧急服务一些部队 比如扑灭森林大火
Such as serving emergency forces in remote areas, like those fighting forest fires.
Starlink可能会更快 但也不可能是一瞬间做到
Starlink may be faster, but it won't be instantaneous,
因此 每颗卫星载有五个光学通信系统
and thus it has 5 optical communication systems on board
确保在任意时刻同时和四颗卫星保持通信
to maintain a steady connection to 4 satellites at all times.
如果我们使用Starlink在纽约和伦敦来回传输数据
If we now use this system, transmitting from New York to London and back,
最短的理论路径 使用真空光速作为传输速度
with the shortest path possible, using the speed of light in a vacuum as our transfer speed,
那么延迟可以低至43毫秒
we can achieve a latency as low as 43 milliseconds.
即使我们使用最短路径上的光纤 虽然这还不存在
Even if we took the shortest route possible with an optic fibre, which does not exist,
这这也要花55毫秒 慢28%
this would take about 55 milliseconds, a 28% decrease in speed.
而这个路程现实中的延迟是76毫秒 前面已经提到过
The actual current return trip time for your average Joe is about 76 milliseconds, as we saw earlier.
慢了77%
A 77% decrease in speed.
这对于位于两地的金融市场来说是一个极大的影响
This is a huge deal for the two financial markets working out of these cities,
几毫秒内可能就差出去上百万美元了
with millions of dollars being moved in fractions of a second,
更低的时延可以在价格波动中获得巨大优势
having a lower latency would provide a massive advantage in capitalizing on price swings.
实际上 这已经不是通信企业花如此大的价钱为这些特定业务提供服务了
In fact, it wouldn't be the first time a communications company
has made a massive investment to specifically serve these groups.
Hibernian快线是一个私营的海底光缆
The Hibernian Express cable is a privately owned optic cable
是目前位于新泽西Secaucus的NY4数据中心
that is currently the lowest latency connection between the NY4 data centre in Secaucus, New Jersey
到位于英国Slough的LD4数据中心延迟最低的线路 只有59.95毫秒
and the LD4 data centre in Slough, England at just 59.95 ms,
比Starlink理想值慢39.4%
39.4% slower than our best time with Starlink.
在它之前的最快纪录是AC-1光缆 延迟65毫秒
The previous best time was held by the AC-1 cable at 65 ms.
为了提升5毫秒的延迟 不惜花费3亿美元去修Hibernian快线
At a cost of 300 million dollars this 5 ms increase in speed was justified to just connect across the Atlantic.
你想想如果能再快17毫秒 那些敏感企业愿意花多少钱来买这个服务
Imagine how much these time sensitive industries will be willing to pay for a 17-ms-increase in speed.
而当我们发现这个延迟差距会随着传输距离增加而增加时 它的价值就更高了
It becomes even more valuable when you realise this time differential increases
with increased transmission distance.
纽约到伦敦距离还算近的
New York to London is a relatively short distance.
对于伦敦到新加坡的传输 提升就更明显了
The improvements would be even more pronounced for a London to Singapore transmission,
距离每提升一点 延迟降低的程度就更多
for every additional kilometre we travel the potential gains in speed increase rapidly.
但太空叉并不仅仅打算让Starlink的快速网络服务某些客户
But SpaceX aren't just planning on serving this super fast internet to some customers,
他们宣传该系统的宗旨是想让地球上每个人都能连接互联网
they primarily advertise this system as a way to connect every human on this planet to the internet,
他们也有很多空余的带宽服务这些人
and they should have plenty of bandwidth left over to serve these people.
虽然互联网技术已经成为人类历史上发展最快的技术
Although the internet has been one of the fastest growing technologies in human history,
但到了2019年年末 全世界仍然有近40亿人没有“上线”
by the end of 2019 more than half of the world's population will still be offline (4 billion).
用户只需花大约200美元 使用Starlink的终端就能连接互联网
Users will connect to this internet using a Starlink terminal which will cost around $200 each,
虽然这还是超出了很多第三世界国家人民的购买力
this will still be far outside the purchasing power of many third world citizens,
但这仅仅是开始 何况这已经比类似的产品便宜很多了
but it's a start and vastly cheaper then similar currently available receivers
比如Kymeta版本的锅盖就要三万美元
like the Kymeta version at a price of $30,000.
马一龙说这种锅盖足够平整 可以放在房顶或车顶
Elon Musk says that these will be flat enough to fit onto the roof of a car
或者其他交通工具 比如船或飞机
and other vehicles like ships and airplanes.
这样 Starlink还可以与传统互联网服务商竞争
This will allow Starlink to compete with traditional internet providers.
据估计 美国从4G升级到5G
It's estimated that moving the US from a 4G to a 5G wireless connection
在未来七年内 要在光缆铺设上要花费1500亿美元
will cost around $150 billion in fiber optic cabling alone over the next 7 years,
而太空叉则要在100亿美元内完成整个Starlink项目
SpaceX plan to complete their entire Starlink project for as little as $10 billion.
每颗Starlink卫星价值约30万美元
Each Starlink satellite cost around $300,000
对于通信卫星来说这已经是白菜批发价了
which is already a massive cut in cost for communication satellites.
太空叉还可以在发射费用上节省 因为他们有自家的猎鹰九号火箭
SpaceX are also saving on launch costs, as they are launching on their own Falcon 9 rocket,
一般的卫星制造商可做不到
something that no other satellite manufacturer has.
如果进展顺利 在高级交易所支持下 Starlink预计每年可盈利300-500亿美元
If everything goes to plan, Starlink is estimated to generate $30 billion to $50 billion in revenue each year
on the back of premium stock exchange memberships,
碾压他们目前每年约30亿美元的利润
demolishing their current annual revenue of around $3 billion.
而这对于马一龙的长期目标是非常重要的
And this is a vital part of Elon Musk's long term goals.
Starlink赚来的钱可以让太空叉有比NASA还多的资金
The money generated from Starlink will mean SpaceX will have vastly more funding than NASA.
可以用于研发新火箭
Which could go on to fund research and development of new rockets
研发未来向月球和火星殖民的技术
and the technology needed to monetise lunar and martian colonies.
目前来讲 Starlink的计划单纯是让世界更加联通
For now the project is simply aiming to connect the world even more
并为互联网不发达的第三世界国家的教育开辟新的道路
and potentially open avenues for education for third world countries
that do not have adequate connections to the internet.